Hi, NZCA. Can you give me a thumbs up if you can hear me? Just a mic check.
And
welcome to the select committee this afternoon, the
Environment Select Committee.
This is the very first of our hearings for the
Conservation Amendment Bill, and we would like to
welcome our first submitter, the New Zealand Conservation
Authority. Welcome to the committee. We can see you there.
We've got Chad, Dean, and Mick. So look, you've got
15 minutes with us this afternoon, so we'll
hand it over to you for some opening remarks and a bit of an introduction.
Do take your submission as read, and I'm sure members will have
some questions. So if you can leave some time at the end for some questions, that
would be great. So over to you.
Madam Chair and members of the committee, tena koutou katoa.
Thank you for the opportunity
to appear before you today on behalf of the New Zealand Conservation
Authority.
The Authority acknowledges the work of the committee in considering this bill and
the many perspectives you will hear throughout this process.
For those unfamiliar with the Authority, we are an independent
statutory body established under the Conservation Act,
responsible for advising the Minister of Conservation and the Department,
approving national conservation planning documents, and reviewing and reporting
on system effectiveness.
My name is Shad Rawlinson, Chair of the Authority, and I'm joined by Mick Abbott
and Dean van Merlo,
both members of the Authority.
The Authority supports reform that improves conservation management while
retaining conservation primacy,
upholding Treaty commitments, preserving independent governance, and maintaining
public participation. To make the best use of our time together,
we've tried to keep our remarks brief, to allow for
those conversations and discussions to occur.
I'll briefly talk about Treaty matters, Mick will pick up on conservation
purpose, and Dean will follow on public participation.
The Authority supports much of what proposed Section
4A seeks to achieve in the bills. Clearer engagement processes,
transparency, and certainty are positive developments.
Our concern is that Section 4A should not unintentionally
become the complete code for Treaty compliance.
Section 4
of the Conservation Act is one of New Zealand's strongest Treaty provisions.
The courts have recognized that it creates substantive obligations capable of
influencing outcomes, not simply procedural requirements.
If compliance with Section 4A comes to be treated as satisfying Section
4, the bill narrows and limits those existing obligations.
Our recommendation is straightforward: clarify that Section 4A establishes
minimum procedural requirements only and does not limit or
replace the wider obligation arising under Section 4.
The Authority is also concerned that proposed Section
14ZG removes the only Treaty-based pathway for
considering
competitive concession processes.
We recommend it be amended so that Treaty rights and interests remain a relevant
consideration for decision-makers.
And a last point in relation to this topic,
the Authority doesn't speak for iwi and hapū when it comes to Treaty settlements.
Our role is institutional.
We seek to ensure Treaty settlement arrangements operating through the Authority
and conservation boards continue to have the same practical and legal
effect.
Many settlements provide for an enhanced role in conservation
decision-making through the Authority and conservation boards.
As the statutory framework changes, the bill should ensure those arrangements
retain equivalent effect, not simply equivalent
consultation processes.
The Authority believes these issues can be addressed through targeted
amendments while fully supporting the bill's broader objective of improved
conservation management.
Madam Chair, I'll pass over to Mick, who will talk about
round-off comments around purpose of the bills.
Kia ora.
The Conservation Authority supports the formulation adopted
in the new Section 6E,
where it retains the Department's recreation function, and it usefully
adds the qualifier to the extent consistent with their conservation.
That correctly establishes conservation as the primary constraint on the
Department's functions on public conservation land.
Our concern is that the new section, Section 6EA,
omits that same qualifier.
Rather, the section requires the Department to enable economic use and
development to the greatest extent practicable under this Act and
other enactments. This is an operational test, and it's rel--
not a conservation test. There is no requirement that
economic use and development be consistent with
conservation. Three consequences follow.
First, there's no hierarchy between the functions.
Section 6EA sits alongside the conservation functions,
not beneath them, and can therefore be balanced against them.
Second, there's no limitation on scale
Significant qualifier.
Third, to the greatest extent practical is a
maximisation imperative. It removes a consistency
constraint. It directs the department towards enabling development
irrespective of conservation outcomes.
The practical effect is to redefine conservation as no longer
focused on preservation and protection, but on enabling use.
Other department to encourage and enable farming, mining, minerals
processing, forestry, solar and wind farms, hydroelectric
dams, et cetera.
It could also mean new hotels, restaurants, gondolas, and visitor centres in
areas of international, national, and regional conservation
significance.
And because the same function is inserted into Sections 13 ,
Section 13
governing area plans, and Section 14 governing
concessions, it flows through the entire management
framework.
We also note that the department's own supplementary analysis report of April
2026 states that conservation will remain the primary
purpose of the Conservation Act, and that the changes are intended to
enable development.
None of this has been translated into the drafting.
The NZCA recommends that the Section 6 be removed,
or if it is to remain, it should be amended to read,
"To recognise the economic opportunities that arise from the
use and development of land and other natural resources and historic
resources managed by the department, and to allow their
use
conservation."
That single change would apply to tourism, to visitor amenity areas,
and to all other economic use and development.
It would require development proposals to demonstrate how conservation benefit
accrues from their implementation.
I'll now pass on to Dean van Melsem to discuss public participation in terms of the
bill.
Good afternoon, Madam Chair, members of the committee.
Improved and more efficient conservation planning processes and greater certainty
and faster turnaround in concession processing are both
legitimate objectives of the Conservation Amendment Bill that the NZCA
supports.
There's no doubt that the conservation planning system can and should be
improved and made more efficient.
Such improvement, however, does not require dismantling the independent
oversight that has underpinned the management of New Zealand's conservation lands
and waters for almost four decades.
Conservation boards throughout the country and the NZCA at a national
level provide independent community-based input and
conservation governance.
Concentrating national policy, regional planning, and concession authority in a
single ministerial office, while simultaneously mandating an economic
development function for all public conservation lands and waters,
fundamentally rewrites the architecture of the Conservation Act and those
acts listed in its first schedule.
Rather than modernising conservation law, the Conservation Amendment Bill
returns us to the early 1980s, where multiple conflicting
conservation and development or use imperatives were
simultaneously sought to be given effect to by government departments.
Under the bill, the minister will set the NCPS, approve all
area plans under it, and make concession decisions, while at the
same time enabling economic development to the greatest extent practicable.
It is to address these sorts of conflicts that the Conservation Act separates
rule setting and rule application.
Conservation boards and the NZCA have an important role in policy and
rule setting. That role is a conduit for community engagement.
Remove the role, and we risk losing that engagement and community buy-in
to the protection and management of our nation's conservation resources.
Outcomes for conservation are known to be more effective and more
enduring where the community is engaged and listened to.
The NZCA recommends that its oversight role as a decision-maker is
retained in the development of the National Conservation Policy Statement,
and that conservation boards,
is retained in respect of conservation area plans under the
Amendment Bill.
The authority considers that watering down the authority and the board's planning
functions to an advisory role only would be
retrograde and counter to progressive and modern
conservation management, which encourages community input and engagement.
We envisage an optimal solution where the NCPS is jointly approved
by the minister and the NZCA,
and subsidiary area plans are approved by conservation boards
consistent with their place-based knowledge and statutory
mandate.
The NZCA supports the retention of targeted public hearings for both
plan-making and concession decision processes.
From a practical perspective, our experience is that hearings convened under the
existing provisions of the Conservation Act are very efficiently
managed and do not suffer the lengthy processes that have become commonplace
in some other forums.
Finally, the NZCA acknowledges that within its memberships, and within the
membership of many conservation boards, there are placements that are the
result of finalized treaty settlements.
The authority is concerned that removing or reducing the statutory role of boards
and the authority risks undermining these existing settlements.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. Look, we have about five minutes for questions,
so we will start with Priyanka.
Thank you. And firstly, I just want to say thank you.
That was an exceptional submission, I thought.
You laid out your rationale really clearly, so thank you for that
I have to choose between two questions now that I have for you.
But I think I'll ask you,
in your written submission in 5.4, I think it
is,
you have suggested that the committee seeks specific evidence of
NZCA or board-caused material delay
before the efficiency rationale is removed,
to ostensibly speed up the process.
Can I ask whether DOC has ever communicated to the
Conservation Authority that there have been delays caused
by the authority?
In my assessment, no.
We have a
statutory role when it comes to approving plans, and we're pretty much toward the
end of the process.
Boards develop plans along with
local DOC,
the local DOC regional area,
and those are developed in partnership with where there are treaty settlement
arrangements.
And then they get passed through particular decision-making
gateways before it ultimately lands in front of the
authority.
I've been on the authority three years, and we've
just approved the Te Hiku CMS at our last
meeting. And I understand that was in about a three-year development
process. We had to pause the West Coast
CMS because of the reform program.
That was in development. And the
last plan that was approved, and it was
an update to an existing plan,
I think was in 2022,
I think. I'll just check with Dean and Mick on those
two matters.
Yeah. Thank you.
If the issue is indeed time frames and delays, and there was
perhaps a specific time frame written into
this legislation, would you be supportive of that?
And what do you think a reasonable time frame for response from NZCA would
be?
I might pass to Dean or to Mick, who might have comments on that.
You can also come back to us.
Yeah, I think it's perfectly good to streamline and to
set a time frame for those things. In
terms of conservation boards, it depends on the facilitation that the department
can give to that process and also working with iwi partners.
For the authority's role in that with the current CMSs that
we've done, I would imagine a six month is sufficient time frame
for doing things.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you. Celia Wade-Brown.
Thank you very much. Thank you for a comprehensive submission.
I've got a couple of questions.
You've got one. You're shuffling around.
I've got more than a couple, but I will ask one.
Yes.
Which is,
the debate about the changes to the Conservation Act
are very much framed as economic versus conservation.
And do you think from your experience, seeing people coming
through using the conservation estate, that the
benefits to mental and physical health for people actually getting
out and about have been
almost ignored in that fight between
conservation and more extractive economic
benefit?
I might pass to Dean. He might be able to share some comments on that one.
Well, my response to that would be undoubtedly those benefits are there,
and they are huge. They are rather intangible, so of course, they're
rather difficult to quantify. Some people have attempted
to and even tried to apply an economic analysis to that.
But I think it's generally accepted that there are
huge benefits
to
the
population at large,
to people getting out and enjoying the public conservation land.
And, I know DOC has made a real
push for promoting that in recent years, and I think that's a real positive
step that we've seen.
Thank you.
I don't know if I can take it further than that.
Thank you. Grant McCallum.
Yeah, just
focusing on the governance and
your role in this space. Given that the
minister is the one ultimately responsible to the public
and for the outcomes of the plans and so forth, shouldn't the
minister therefore have the final say?
I think reflecting on history and why the
NZCA and the authorities were put in place, it was to manage the
tension between, at the time, pre-DOC, you've got liens and survey,
you've got forestry department looking after assets, and there was
this inherent tension between economic development and preservation.
And
I suppose the way the bills are framed, we could potentially be heading back into
that inherent tension within
conservation around how we manage
our important spaces and
resources. At the same time, the tension and the
push for development. So the role of the authority was to create
that separation,
along with the conservation boards, but also to provide
for public voice in these processes.
Yeah, but ultimately, they can still do that, but give the minister the final say,
since ultimately the minister is the one who has to go out and
show the public. Because they're the ones that are directly
responsible to the public in the end.
Yes. Yeah, and I appreciate that. I think this gives that
level of separation and particularly that political
dynamic that occurs. The Conservation Authority has a
stewardship role in terms of holding a space for all
New Zealanders, regardless of the political environment that New
Zealand sits in.
I'd add just in that, the
conservation boards represent the public in
their public conservation lands, but the board members and the authority
members are actually appointed by the Minister of Conservation.
Thank you. Look, I'm just going to quickly jump in because I'm quite interested in
the recommendation around 6E .
And obviously you have said that you'd like to see it removed,
otherwise, amended, so that economic development
activities must be consistent with conservation.
Did you have any kind of wording or any kind of further thoughts
around
tying those together?
We've suggested at the end there some specific wording for
that.
And in terms of that consistent with conservation,
we feel that makes available many opportunities
within tourism and other areas,
but making sure that conservation is prioritized and
benefits from any such activities.
Okay. Thank you. And we'll just take one last quick question from Scott.
Yeah. Thank you. Thank you all. It's related to those other two
questions. Essentially, the point that you make about the lack of hierarchy
in 6E is something that we can see
the risk with that. And I really just want to get your sense of
what do you think
could be the effect of this for our tourism
dollar, for people who come to Aotearoa for the clean green
image, for the unique experiences they can have in our wilderness.
What do you think could be the effect if we don't
have that conservation value at top of the
hierarchy?
Pass to Dean or to Mick.
I'll just add in there, I think that
having that consistent with conservation, I think
would provide wonderful focus for tourism and other interests to-
Mm
...
to continue that development and promotion of
tourism. That is actually why people are coming here.
So we don't see that as a conflict rather than an
alignment.
That's great. Look-
Yeah. I'd concur with that, and I'd just briefly add that I think there is great
reputational risk to New Zealand's hard-earned reputation.
We've marketed ourselves on 100% pure, et cetera.
And
potentially if we undermine that, I think the consequences could be quite
significant.
Look, thank you very much. We are going to have to leave it there.
We've met time. We really appreciate your submission, a really valuable
submission with a lot to think about there. So, thank you very much.
Thank you.
So that brings us to the end of our public hearings on the
Conservation Amendment Bill